one of the big projects you worked on at
Dropbox was my migrating away from S3.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> So, um you know, why why did Dropbox
migrate away from S3?
>> Yeah, that was a desire of the company
for a long time. You know, from even
before I was there. So, I started at
Dropbox in 20 uh 2012.
Um and I spoke to to Drew, the Dropbox
founder, I think in 2010 about this
project. And so, I think there was a
desire to um control the destiny of the
company from a strategic perspective. at
the time, it was before Dropbox kind of
reshaped itself as being more about
collaboration, you know, but at the time
it was a file sync and share category.
That was that was the that was the that
was the market sector, you know? And so,
and owning the file system was really
valuable to the company.
Ultimately, we saved a huge amount of
money. I mean, we we And this is before
the public company went public. We
really drove massive cost efficiencies
through the project. Um but it was hard,
you know, in a way that I think it'd be
very difficult to to emulate without a
huge investment.
And I do think that there is um
there is a benefit to an organization
from having hard problems to solve.
Because if you have a a company with
extremely hard technical challenges, you
can
attract engineers who like working on
those hard technical problems. And when
they've solved those problems, they
cycle off and work on different parts of
the system. So, you know, after we all
worked we had a such a great team. It
was a very very small engineering team.
And after we kind of shipped the the
storage system reliably, we all went off
and, you know, Jamie went and and
redesigned the sync protocol, the
desktop client, and I worked on the on
the file system and the distributed
databases. And so, yeah, there's there's
value to a business to have um that
level of technical investment, but it is
a
you know, it's like it's like having a
baby and then you have to you've got to
raise the baby. You can't just build a
system like this and be that's it, we're
done.
You own it and you have to keep
investing in it.
>> Did um
did S3 do any counter negotiation before
you set out to leave them? Did they say
like, "Oh, you know, we'll cut you a
deal if you stay."
>> [laughter]
>> I guess I'm allowed to talk about this
now. It was a long time ago. Um
yeah, for the longest time there I don't
think they were they were particularly
aware that this was happening.
Um but you know, the the data center
folks talk and uh certainly it was
noticed that Dropbox was buying up a lot
of data center space. So, yeah, we had
we had um obviously at at the scales
that we were at, I mean, we were
negotiating very good rates with Amazon.
You know, we weren't paying sticker
price, we're paying very very very good
discounted rates. Um but yeah, at a
certain point they weren't able to meet
our cost efficiency because it it's when
we launched the system, it really was
more efficient than S3.
And that's for a variety of reasons. One
was that we were using kind of new
experimental disks called shingled
magnetic recording. We were the first
ones I think to use these disks at
scale.
Um and two, we had a very tight
understanding of our workloads. So, we
were able to design the system
specifically optimized for our
workloads, whereas S3 has to design the
system for everybody. So, you know,
it's it got to the point where, you
know, Amazon would not have been able to
offer us a more competitive deal because
we had a more efficient system.
Um
I wouldn't recommend another company do
this right now.
Uh but I think at the time it it
certainly made sense for us as a
company.
>> Can you give an example of a tight
understanding of your workloads leading
to like something you could do that S3
couldn't?
>> Yeah, absolutely. So, for example, I
know
that um well, I'll try not to leak any
confidential data, right? But when you
when you upload a file to Dropbox, there
is a pattern of access, right? Um so,
typically people um access the file very
quickly shortly afterwards um because
you're sharing it with someone, or maybe
your Dropbox is processing that file to
generate an image preview, and then it
decays at a certain rate. And so we
understand in general the average block
size, and we understand also the access
pattern. So we could do things like at a
certain point we had these two clusters.
One was One was
designed for kind of temporary storage.
That was kind of storage inefficient,
but access efficient. So it was very
cheap to read and write to, but it was
inefficient to store. And data would get
written to there first, and then in the
background it would get moved in bulk to
this colder storage system.
And this colder storage system was far
more static.
And so it was able to have kind of more
efficient algorithms and and and be
written to in bulk. And if it went down
for rights, that was no problems because
it wasn't in the live path. And so we're
able to trade off again, like systems is
all about trade-offs. So we're able to
trade off the the live data write path
from the long-term read path.
That's one of many examples where
knowing the size of your data, where
it's accessed from, how frequently it
gets accessed, how how long it takes to
delete that data, you can really tune a
system
to your workload. If you know, stuff
like looking at
um
even things down to knowing how much
power to put in a rack. You know, you
have a rack of hardware there's a power
distribution unit, a PDU, at the top of
that rack. It has a circuit breaker
which can handle a certain number of
amps.
We would have to figure out, you know,
how many amps are required for that rack
based on access patterns. And there were
times where we got it slightly wrong.
There was times where
we got to maybe a bad batch of hardware,
and disks were failing too frequently.
And as a result we were re-replicating
the data
more regularly, and I was getting you
know, messages from the data center team
saying, "Hey,
we're running the racks really hot right
now, you know?" [laughter] So, that's
the level of optimizations you can make
when you get to that scale. Um but
again, that's multi-exabyte scale, you
know,
million hard drive scale.
>> Yeah, when I was reading about this
migration, I saw somewhere in the
migration
you initially started with Go, and then
the racks or something that you're
running on the hardware itself was
ooming too much or
>> Yeah.
>> requesting too much memory, and then you
migrated to Rust.
>> So, initially, the prototype was in
Python, if you can believe that.
And to be fair, Python is actually
pretty efficient for IO. I think people
give Python a a bad rap for IO-bound
workloads. It's pretty good at IO. Um
but obviously, um not great for
concurrency, not great for memory
management, and um very hard to
refactor.
And it was critical the system was
correct. And so, we migrated everything
to Go, and we built most of the storage
system in Go. This was before Go was in
general availability. I think this is
before Go was GA. Um
and we built the system in Go. Go is a
great language for concurrency, a great
language for proxies. You know, it's a
really well designed for like servers
that moved out of one place to another
place.
At a certain point though,
we would have, you know, let's just pick
a number. Let's say a million. Let's say
we have a million nodes in the system.
And every node has um
some amount of memory, some amount of
disk, some amount of sheet metal in the
chassis, right? And we would itemize all
these things. You'd have a pie chart of
of how much money is spent on all the
things. And it would still have stuff
like, yeah, sheet metal and screws and
stuff. And so, you're trying to optimize
the storage, and a big problem for us
was the amount of memory um
these nodes were using. Not just the
memory they were using, but the
unpredictability of it. Uh with, you
know, with Go having a runtime and and
you know, in a storage system an out of
memory error is pretty bad.
Because if a node runs out of memory and
restarts, that looks like a disk
failure.
So that looks a lot like a disk has
failed and has to be re-replicated. And
so a batch of nodes OOMing
can lead to cascading failures
throughout the system.
Because maybe
um
I remember a time it was a band, it
might have been De La Soul. I can't
remember there was a band released an
album on Dropbox.
So there was a big spike in load
um to a to a
a few files. So it was very, very high
um bandwidth and it caused them the
machines to OOM. So that those machines
uh OOMed, those disks OOMed. Um and so
as a result, no problems. The system
went to try to recover that data from a
whole bunch of other replicas, right?
Now all of a sudden you've taken one
amount one fire hose worth of load
coming in and you've turned this into
seven fire hoses worth of load coming
cuz now you have to do a more expensive
reconstruction operation, right? So now
you've seven Xed the load. And these are
the kind of um cyclical kind of
behaviors that can lead to something
called congestion collapse. Congestion
collapse is when
workload to a system crosses a threshold
where it all kind of collapses.
So can you design against congestion
collapse is really the hardest part or
one of the hardest parts of Magic
Pocket, which is the name of the storage
system.
Um so ultimately we switched to Rust for
the storage nodes themselves. And this
again, this is before Rust was in GA, so
that was a bit of a risky move. Uh
but we rewrote um
the switch to Rust coincided with
getting rid of the file system entirely
on the disks and directly addressing the
the disk disk heads. So there was a
there's an instruction set, I think it's
called ZBC, zone based block control,
something like that. There's there's a
there's an instruction set for accessing
disks that we were using.
The disk manufacturers gave us the draft
specs of these new disks and we were
operating off the draft specs and
directly controlling the the disks. And
so,
all that product was tied up um together
um
into a product called DiscoTech.
It was the disk technology project. Um
and ultimately, if you look at that pie
chart, one congestion collapse stopped
and reliability improved. But if you
looked at the pie chart of where all the
money was going, it really shifted to be
almost all disks. And what we wanted to
do is get that pie chart to be
almost all the money spent on disks and
as little money spent on RAM, on
compute, on network, on power, on sheet
metal, etc.
>> The cascading failure you mentioned, was
there So, that that happened and then
there was a postmortem.
>> I don't think we needed a postmortem. I
think we we knew as it was happening.
>> [laughter]
>> I think when I was getting paged in the
middle of the night on these things, I
would you know you'd be pretty pretty
evident. And so, look, this is the
Again, this is an argument in favor of
the cloud. All right. Imagine you've
spent
hundreds of millions of dollars on a on
a storage system and it's out in
production and it's on physical
hardware.
You can't just go and put new memory
chips in every one of them. I mean, you
can, but you have to pay people to come
in and swap them out, you know? And so,
that's a tricky place. And so, as a And
this is what This is what I love about
industry. You know, cuz in like some of
the more um
challenging moments on magic pocket were
stuff like In one week,
just a weird coincidence, two trucks
crashed that were delivering servers.
So, there's two trucks showing up to
deliver racks and they both crashed. I
don't know, you know, the drivers were
okay. So, we lost capacity for 2 weeks.
Uh so So, we lost capacity for for more
than 2 weeks for for for probably 6
weeks.
Um
How What do you do?
What happens, you know, is is the
equivalent of your disk filling up on
your laptop, except it's you know, it's
it's a million disks.
And you can't tell the customers to go
away. You can't delete their files. So,
a lot of a lot of tricky
a lot of tricky capacity work.
And ultimately what that what that led
to was trying to build in
all these protections against the
unknowns. You know, making sure we had
the right amount of buffer planned out
for anything bad that could happen.
Making sure we we design the system so
they couldn't be congestion collapsed so
they wouldn't be memory spikes.
Um and
you know, at one point there's a there's
a process called I think it's called
FMEA,
which is like a threat modeling process
where you had a big spreadsheet and you
kind of write down every bad thing that
could possibly happen and then, you
know, all the how bad it would be if it
happened.
Existential risk
to someone die, you know, if there's a
fire in the data center. All these kind
of things get put into the spreadsheet.
And you kind of do a bit of a almost
pre-mortem kind of a work to figure out
all the all the potential failure modes
and then design around them. And I
that's I love that work. I I really um
I don't know. I do like the firefight. I
I like the
I don't I can't say I like getting paged
because
I've spent my whole life on call,
but I do like that rubber hits the road
stuff. I like that
wow, there's congestion collapse and and
there's no one that can help you. And so
you've got to
think through this problem.
>> When I worked on infrastructure at
Instagram, we had this concept of DEFCON
knobs, which are basically these configs
that you could flip that would
gracefully degrade your system where you
can still operate it, but you know,
maybe in the case of Dropbox, you store
less replicas. So, you take on a
temporary increase of
risk in losing data because you need to.
Did you have something like that and did
you flip it in that type of case?
>> Never when it came to durability. So, I
mean, we just had an just absolute zero
non-negotiable like there was no room
for negotiation on on users' durability.
And so, um
we had those knobs for background
processes for CPU and and memory, for
example. So, if there was like a spike
in load, you could turn off background
processes and and turn off um you know,
um the the test load, for example, on
the system. Eventually, we we built this
system called
trampoline.
And what trampoline did was um which
actually was a it it saved us a ton of
money, right? When if we ever got too
close to the threshold, we would just
start writing data to S3.
Cuz it's right there, right? So, it's um
you can run your capacity way closer to
the edge if you're willing under
worst-case scenarios just to just to
dump 30 petabytes on S3 and then move it
back when it's done. And now, it did it
didn't happen very often. We would do it
to test it. We would do that just to
make sure the system worked.
But, um yeah, being able to have a
escape hatch for worst-case scenario was
really nice.
>> I see. So, S3 is kind of um
it's like elastic storage.
>> Exactly.